Hello everyone and welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And my name is Kathryn and it is the holiday season.
我是Kathryn，现在是假日季节。
That means we're talking about Christmas and Christmas shopping.
这意味着我们要谈论圣诞节和圣诞购物。
We've got a great lesson for you today.
今天我们为大家准备了一堂很棒的课。
Exactly.
没错。
So we're going to be looking for a Christmas gift and so let's listen to our dialogue for
所以我们要去找一份圣诞礼物，先听一遍我们的对话，
the first time and we'll be back to explain some words.
然后我们会回来解释一些单词。
Bill, Bill, you've got to help me.
Bill，Bill，你得帮帮我。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Slow down or you're going to give yourself a heart attack.
慢点，不然你会心脏病发作的。
Tomorrow is Christmas and I haven't bought my mom anything.
明天就是圣诞节了，我还没给我妈买任何东西。
I'm such a bad son.
我真是个不孝的儿子。
Take it easy.
别紧张。
Let's go to the mall, window shop a little and see if there's anything she might like.
我们去商场逛逛橱窗，看看有没有她可能喜欢的东西。
That's just it.
问题就在这儿。
I don't know what to get her.
我不知道该给她买什么。
Last year I got her a ring that was two sizes too big and a pair of shoes five sizes too
去年我给她买了一枚戒指，大了两号，还有一双鞋，小了五号。
small.
I suck at getting presents for people.
我送礼物真的很差劲。
That's where you're making a big mistake.
这就是你犯大错的地方。
You can't just guess people's likes or sizes, especially with clothes or jewelry.
你不能光靠猜别人的喜好或尺寸，尤其是衣服或珠宝。
On top of that, I think that you should get your mom something that shows how much you
除此之外，我觉得你应该给你妈买一件能表达你有多爱她的东西。
love her.
At the same time, you should show her that you took the time and effort to look for something
同时，你应该让她看到你花了时间和精力去找一件她真正喜欢的东西。
that she would really like.
Yeah, you're right.
是啊，你说得对。
When it comes down to it, I can be pretty tacky.
说到底，我可能挺俗气的。
Yeah, tell me about it.
是啊，可不是嘛。
I know.
我知道。
Your mom is trying to learn Spanish, right?
你妈正在学西班牙语，对吧？
Why don't you get her a gift certificate for this great website I saw called SpanishPod?
不如给她买一张这个叫SpanishPod的网站的礼品券吧？
Now that's a great idea.
这主意真不错。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now, why don't we take a look at Language Takeaway.
现在，我们来看看“语言要点”部分。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
Okay, so there are a lot of interesting words in this dialogue.
好的，这段对话里有很多有趣的单词。
Some of them have to do with Christmas and some of them have to do with shopping.
有些和圣诞节有关，有些和购物有关。
So this first one has to do with neither.
第一个词两者都不沾边。
It's actually a phrase.
实际上是一个短语。
It's a medical term.
是一个医学术语。
Right.
对。
He talked about a heart attack.
他提到了心脏病发作。
Okay, so you know what a heart is, but a heart attack is when there's no more blood going
好的，你知道心脏是什么，但心脏病发作是指没有血液流进心脏，心脏停止跳动。
into your heart and your heart stops beating.
It's a very, very dangerous situation.
这是一个非常非常危险的情况。
So the person actually said this because the other guy was like, Bill, Bill, you got to
所以那个人这么说是因为另一个人像这样：Bill，Bill，你得帮帮我。
help me.
He was all very excited.
他非常激动。
He was like, whoa, whoa, slow down or you're going to give yourself a heart attack.
他就像：哇，哇，慢点，不然你会心脏病发作的。
So it's not literal, right?
所以这不是字面意思，对吧？
Yeah, it's not a real heart attack.
对，不是真的心脏病发作。
He's saying, calm down.
他是在说：冷静点。
Calm down.
冷静点。
Okay.
好的。
Alright.
好了。
And well, he was very upset because he hadn't bought a gift and he said, I suck at getting
嗯，他因为没买礼物而很沮丧，他说：我送礼物真的很差劲。
presents for people.
I suck at getting presents for people.
我送礼物真的很差劲。
Well, suck is not a very polite word.
嗯，“suck”不是一个很礼貌的词。
My mom used to get angry at me when I used it, but it's a way to say that I'm very, very
我妈妈以前用这个词时会生我的气，但它是用来表示我做某事非常非常差劲。
bad at doing something.
Okay, so I suck at playing tennis.
好的，比如我打网球很差劲。
Alright, or you can say, I suck at math.
好了，或者你可以说：我数学很差劲。
Alright, but again, this is not something you should use on a test or in an essay because
好了，但再说一次，这不是你在考试或作文里应该用的词，因为它是非常口语化的英语。
it's very spoken colloquial English.
Right, exactly.
对，没错。
And this other word is actually okay to use and when you're talking about presents or
而另一个词实际上是可以用的，当你谈论礼物或装饰品时，你会说某样东西很俗气。
you're talking about decorations, you say something is tacky.
Okay, well, if you call something tacky, this is an adjective, so something is tacky, it's
好的，如果你说某样东西俗气，这是一个形容词，所以某样东西俗气，这其实是个主观看法。
really a matter of opinion.
Okay, so I think this is tacky, but you don't.
好的，所以我觉得这个俗气，但你不觉得。
Maybe that's a problem.
这可能是个问题。
So let me give you an example of tacky.
让我给你举个例子说明什么是俗气。
I think that clothing with lots of bows and glitter and shiny things are very tacky.
我觉得有很多蝴蝶结、亮片和闪亮东西的衣服很俗气。
Okay, so it's something that you don't really like.
好的，所以这是你不喜欢的东西。
So you think that is a little bit strange.
所以你觉得这有点奇怪。
That's right.
没错。
So as you say, it's an opinion because you think that clothes with bows and teddy bears
所以就像你说的，这是个主观看法，因为你觉得有蝴蝶结和泰迪熊的衣服很俗气。
on it is tacky.
Well, somebody else can think, no, it's cute, it's nice.
嗯，别人可能觉得：不，这很可爱，很好看。
Exactly.
没错。
And you can also describe things that people do as being tacky.
你也可以用“tacky”来形容人们做的事情。
So for example, he gave me a present but he left the price on it.
比如，他给了我一份礼物，但价格标签还留在上面。
Oh, that is so tacky.
哦，那太俗气了。
Right, that is tacky.
对，那很俗气。
Alright, so the word is tacky.
好了，所以这个词是“tacky”。
And moving on, we talked about a gift certificate.
接下来，我们谈到了礼品券。
You should get your mom a gift certificate.
你应该给你妈买一张礼品券。
Well, a gift certificate is a very popular form of gift giving now.
嗯，礼品券现在是一种很流行的送礼方式。
You know what a gift is, but a certificate is a piece of paper.
你知道礼物是什么，但证书是一张纸。
Okay, so you could have a birth certificate, for example, it says when you were born, where
好的，比如你可以有出生证明，上面写着你的出生时间和地点。
you were born.
But in this case, a gift certificate is a piece of paper that you give someone to say,
但在这里，礼品券是一张你给别人，表示“你有这么多钱可以在这家店花”的纸。
you have this much money to spend at this store.
So I could give my mom a gift certificate for a bookstore for $50 and she can go with
所以我可以给我妈一张书店的50美元礼品券，她可以拿着这张纸免费花50美元，因为我已经付过钱了。
this piece of paper and spend $50 for free because I already paid.
So it's kind of a very popular thing to do because sometimes, as in the dialogue, you
所以这是一种很流行的事情，因为有时候，就像对话里一样，你不知道别人的尺寸，或者不知道他们是否喜欢这个颜色。
don't know the person's size or you don't know if they like this color.
So you're just like, look, here's a gift certificate for $100, go to the store that I know you
所以你就说：看，这是一张100美元的礼品券，去我知道你真正喜欢的店，给自己买点好东西。
really like and get yourself whatever you want, something nice.
But it's less tacky than giving that person cash, right?
但这比直接给现金要少俗气一点，对吧？
Right.
对。
Cash is considered a tacky gift.
现金被认为是一种俗气的礼物。
I'm not really sure why, it just is.
我不太确定为什么，但就是这样。
It's a social custom, but very popular right now are these gift certificates or even gift
这是一种社会习俗，但现在非常流行的是这些礼品券，甚至是礼品卡。
cards.
They look like credit cards.
它们看起来像信用卡。
Very good.
非常好。
All right, so why don't we listen to our dialogue again and we'll return shortly to take a look
好了，我们再来听一遍对话，然后很快回来看看“流利度提升”部分。
at Fluency Builder.
Bill Bill you gotta help me.
Bill，Bill，你得帮帮我。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Slow down or you're going to give yourself a heart attack.
慢点，不然你会心脏病发作的。
Tomorrow's Christmas and I haven't bought my mom anything.
明天就是圣诞节了，我还没给我妈买任何东西。
I'm such a bad son.
我真是个不孝的儿子。
Take it easy.
别紧张。
Let's go to the mall, window shop a little and see if there's anything she might like.
我们去商场逛逛橱窗，看看有没有她可能喜欢的东西。
That's just it.
问题就在这儿。
I don't know what to get her.
我不知道该给她买什么。
Last year I got her a ring that was two sizes too big and a pair of shoes five sizes too
去年我给她买了一个戒指，大了两号，还有一双鞋，小了五号。
small.
小。
I suck at getting presents for people.
我送礼物真的很差劲。
That's where you're making a big mistake.
这就是你犯大错的地方。
You can't just guess people's likes or sizes, especially with clothes or jewelry.
你不能光靠猜别人的喜好或尺寸，尤其是衣服或首饰。
On top of that, I think that you should get your mom something that shows how much you
除此之外，我觉得你应该给你妈妈买点能表达你有多爱她的东西。
love her.
爱她。
At the same time, you should show her that you took the time and effort to look for something
同时，你应该让她看到你花了时间和精力去找她真正喜欢的东西。
that she would really like.
她会真正喜欢的。
Yeah, you're right.
是啊，你说得对。
When it comes down to it, I can be pretty tacky.
说到底，我有时候挺俗气的。
Yeah, tell me about it.
是啊，可不是嘛。
I know.
我知道。
Your mom is trying to learn Spanish, right?
你妈妈正在学西班牙语，对吧？
Why don't you get her a gift certificate for this great website I saw called SpanishPod?
不如给她买一张我看到的那个叫SpanishPod的网站的礼品券？
Now that's a great idea.
这主意真不错。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now why don't we take a look at four key phrases on Fluency Builder.
现在，我们来看看Fluency Builder上的四个关键短语。
Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder。
Okay, I like this first phrase.
好，我喜欢第一个短语。
Sometimes I have to use it about other people.
有时候我得用它来说别人。
Sometimes people use it on me.
有时候别人用它来说我。
You say, take it easy.
你说，take it easy。
Take it easy.
Take it easy。
Hey, take it easy.
嘿，take it easy。
Relax.
放松点。
Yeah, this is a way to say, hey, be calm.
对，这是一种说“嘿，冷静点”的方式。
Be calm.
冷静点。
Yeah.
对。
So there's no, you can't really translate it, right?
所以这没法直译，对吧？
Take what easy?
把什么放轻松？
You can't, but this is, there are two main contexts, okay?
不能直译，但这有两种主要语境，好吗？
There are two situations where this is really popular.
有两种情况特别常用。
One is this, oh my God, Marco.
一种是这样的：哦，天哪，Marco。
Oh my God, I'm freaking out.
哦，天哪，我快疯了。
I really need your help on this and I really need you to just really be involved.
我真的需要你帮忙，我真的需要你参与进来。
Take it easy.
Take it easy。
All right, relax.
好了，放松点。
Take it easy.
Take it easy。
Okay.
好。
All right, so that's someone who's upset and you're telling them to calm down.
好了，所以这是对心烦的人说，让他们冷静下来。
The second situation is when you're saying goodbye to someone.
第二种情况是跟人道别的时候。
This is a very kind of, again, spoken language, very comfortable way of saying, hey, see you
这是一种很口语化、很随意的说法，相当于“嘿，回头见”。
later.
回头见。
Right.
对。
So it's like, all right, bye.
所以就像“好了，拜拜”。
Take it easy.
Take it easy。
Yeah, take it easy.
对，take it easy。
Have a good one.
祝你愉快。
Yeah.
对。
Have a good one is another good phrase.
“Have a good one”是另一个好短语。
Take it easy.
Take it easy。
That means, that means, yeah.
意思是，意思是，对。
Take life easy.
生活放轻松。
Don't rush.
别着急。
Yeah.
对。
Enjoy your life.
享受生活。
So if you try this with your English speaking friends, you're saying goodbye, you say,
所以如果你跟说英语的朋友试试这个，道别时说：
hey, take it easy.
嘿，take it easy。
Yeah, bye.
对，拜拜。
Take it easy.
Take it easy。
Bye.
拜拜。
It's a nice one.
这个不错。
Very nice.
非常好。
All right.
好了。
And her second phrase is actually, it's interesting because when he talked about the ring that
第二个短语其实挺有意思的，因为他提到给他妈妈买的戒指大了两号，鞋子小了五号。
he got for her mom that was two sizes too big and a pair of shoes five sizes too small.
他给他妈妈买的戒指大了两号，鞋子小了五号。
So the construction there, two sizes too big, five sizes too small.
所以这个结构是“两号太大”、“五号太小”。
This is a very important construction and it doesn't quite make sense when you hear
这是一个非常重要的结构，刚听到时可能不太明白。
it.
它。
So that's what we're going to explain right now.
所以我们现在就来解释一下。
Let me try to explain this using an example.
让我举个例子来解释。
If I have a size seven shoe and my brother gives me a Christmas present of size nine
如果我穿七号鞋，我哥哥送我九号鞋作为圣诞礼物。
shoes, I say, Peter, these shoes are two sizes too big.
我会说，Peter，这双鞋大了两号。
Okay.
好。
That's the number two, two sizes, T-O-O, too big.
这是数字二，两号，T-O-O，太大。
That means they're too big for me by two sizes.
意思是它们比我大了两号。
Okay.
好。
Because the difference between seven and nine is two.
因为七和九的差是二。
Right.
对。
And if I have a size five shoe, I say, Peter, these shoes are two sizes too small.
如果我穿五号鞋，我会说，Peter，这双鞋小了两号。
That means that five is two less than seven.
意思是五比七少二。
So this is a very popular construction.
所以这是一个很常用的结构。
So you're saying specifically how much bigger or how much smaller the shoes are in the case
所以你是具体说鞋子大了多少或小了多少，比如戒指或鞋子这类有尺寸的东西。
with the ring or shoes or anything that has a size.
戒指或鞋子这类有尺寸的东西。
Exactly.
没错。
But the funny thing is you can also exaggerate.
但有趣的是，你也可以夸张地说。
You could say, oh, this sweater is so ugly.
你可以说，哦，这件毛衣太丑了。
It's 10 sizes too big for me.
它大了十号。
It's not really 10 sizes.
其实不是真的十号。
Right.
对。
So, but you can use this construction, right?
所以你可以用这个结构，对吧？
Using one size too big, etc.
比如“大了一号”等等。
Even when you're buying something to the store, to the lady in the store, you can say, oh,
甚至在商店买东西时，对店员说：哦，我觉得这双鞋大了两号。
I think the shoe is two sizes too big.
哦，我觉得这双鞋大了两号。
Can you give me a smaller pair?
能给我小一号的吗？
Exactly.
没错。
All right.
好了。
And our third phrase for today, when the person said, yeah, you're right.
今天第三个短语，当那个人说“是啊，你说得对”。
When it comes down to it, I can be pretty tacky.
说到底，我有时候挺俗气的。
So we looked at tacky, but what does he mean when it comes down to it?
我们讲了tacky，但“when it comes down to it”是什么意思？
Okay.
好。
Well, this it is very confusing sometimes when we talk about phrases in English, but
嗯，这个“it”在英语短语里有时很让人困惑，但“when it comes down to it”是一种说法，意思是“实际上”或“事实上”，或者“真相是”。
when it comes down to it as a way to say in reality or actually, or the truth is yes.
实际上或事实上，或者真相是。
So it's a way to say something is truthful.
所以这是一种表达真实情况的方式。
Okay.
好。
So I can say when it comes down to it, Catherine is a good friend.
所以我可以这样说：说到底，Catherine是个好朋友。
Oh, right.
哦，对。
So when times are tough or in the end, or actually maybe you have your small faults,
所以当困难时刻或最终，或者实际上你可能有小缺点，但你是个好朋友。
but you are a good friend.
但你是个好朋友。
Right.
对。
And when it comes down to it, Marco is a really hard worker.
说到底，Marco是个很努力的人。
So sometimes he likes to play video games, but when it's a really important, he will
所以有时候他喜欢玩电子游戏，但遇到真正重要的事时，他会非常努力。
work really hard.
他会非常努力。
Very good.
非常好。
So very good uses of this phrase and you can use it in many different contexts.
所以这个短语用法很好，可以在很多不同语境中使用。
And for our fourth phrase, when the person said, yeah, tell me about it.
第四个短语，当那个人说“是啊，tell me about it”。
What does it mean?
这是什么意思？
Tell me about it.
可不是嘛。
Tell me about what?
可不是什么？
Okay.
好的。
Well, this is a really very popular phrase.
嗯，这确实是一个非常流行的短语。
You hear this all the time and it's, it's a way to say, yeah, I agree.
你经常能听到它，它是一种表达“是啊，我同意”的方式。
I understand.
我明白。
So this is, this is a phrase that means agreement.
所以这是一个表示同意的短语。
Okay.
好的。
So I can say, God, I really hate winter because when I leave work, it's always really dark.
所以我可以这样说：天哪，我真的很讨厌冬天，因为下班时天总是很黑。
Yeah.
是啊。
Tell me about it.
可不是嘛。
It's always dark and it makes me feel lazy.
天总是黑的，让我觉得很懒散。
Right.
对。
And so Marco is agreeing.
所以Marco是在表示同意。
He says, I don't like it either.
他说：我也不喜欢。
Yeah.
是啊。
So this is a very, very spoken way, spoken language way of agreeing with someone.
所以这是一种非常口语化的、表示同意的方式。
So you say, yeah, tell me about it.
所以你就说：是啊，可不是嘛。
Right.
对。
It's very natural.
这非常自然。
It's a very natural way of agreeing with someone.
这是一种非常自然的表示同意的方式。
Right.
对。
Exactly.
没错。
All right.
好的。
So great phrases.
所以是很棒的短语。
Why don't we take a look at our dialogue for the last time and we'll be back to talk a
我们最后再看一遍对话，然后回来再聊
little bit more.
一会儿。
Bill, Bill, you gotta help me.
Bill，Bill，你得帮帮我。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Slow down or you're going to give yourself a heart attack.
慢点，不然你会心脏病发作的。
Tomorrow's Christmas and I haven't bought my mom anything.
明天就是圣诞节了，我还没给我妈买任何东西。
I'm such a bad son.
我真是个不孝的儿子。
Take it easy.
别紧张。
Let's go to the mall, window shop a little and see if there's anything she might like.
我们去商场，随便逛逛，看看有没有她可能会喜欢的东西。
That's just it.
问题就在这儿。
I don't know what to get her.
我不知道该给她买什么。
Last year I got her a ring that was two sizes too big and a pair of shoes five sizes too
去年我给她买了个戒指，大了两号，还有一双鞋，小了五号
small.
太小了。
I suck at getting presents for people.
我送礼物真的很差劲。
That's where you're making a big mistake.
这就是你犯大错的地方。
You can't just guess people's likes or sizes, especially with clothes or jewelry.
你不能光靠猜别人的喜好或尺码，尤其是衣服或珠宝。
On top of that, I think that you should get your mom something that shows how much you
除此之外，我觉得你应该给你妈妈买一件能表达你有多
love her.
爱她的东西。
At the same time, you should show her that you took the time and effort to look for something
同时，你应该让她看到你花了时间和精力去找一件
that she would really like.
她真正会喜欢的东西。
Yeah, you're right.
是啊，你说得对。
When it comes down to it, I can be pretty tacky.
说到底，我可能挺俗气的。
Yeah.
是啊。
Tell me about it.
可不是嘛。
I know.
我知道。
Your mom is trying to learn Spanish, right?
你妈妈正在学西班牙语，对吧？
Why don't you get her a gift certificate for this great website I saw called SpanishPod?
你为什么不给她买一张这个叫SpanishPod的网站的礼品券呢？
Now that's a great idea.
这主意真不错。
All right, great.
好的，太好了。
So now that the Christmas.
所以现在圣诞节...
All right.
好的。
So as we said, gift certificates are a good idea, but what else do you like to give as
所以就像我们说的，礼品券是个好主意，但你还喜欢送什么作为
Christmas presents?
圣诞礼物呢？
Personally, I like things that people really think about and spend their time doing or
就我个人而言，我喜欢那些人们真正用心思考、花时间去做或
making.
制作的东西。
So I like, for example, my mom is a beautiful quilter.
所以我喜欢，比如，我妈妈是个很棒的拼布爱好者。
She makes these big blankets and quilts them.
她会做这些大毯子，然后缝上拼布。
And sometimes she even quilts names of people and stuff.
有时她甚至会在上面缝上人名之类的东西。
And so those are really wonderful gifts because the person thinks about you and who you are
所以那些真的是很棒的礼物，因为那个人会想到你、你是谁
and what you want.
以及你想要什么。
And so I like to be able to give gifts like that, but I'm not necessarily that creative.
所以我很希望能送出这样的礼物，但我不一定有那么有创意。
So I think it's nice to give gifts like tickets to a music show or things like that where
所以我觉得送像音乐会门票之类的东西也不错，你知道那个人会去
you know the person will go and have a good time and enjoy themselves.
玩得很开心。
Yeah, I think that's really important because sometimes people just give gifts because you
是啊，我觉得这真的很重要，因为有时候人们送礼物只是因为
have to.
不得不送。
Stuff.
东西。
Yeah, like stuff.
是啊，就像东西。
And you're like, oh, great.
然后你就会想：哦，太好了。
A tie.
一条领带。
It's kind of impersonal.
有点缺乏人情味。
At the same time, if your dad or your boyfriend or somebody loves ties and has 50 of them
同时，如果你爸爸或你男朋友或某人很喜欢领带，已经有50条了，
and you get them another one that's really interesting or unique, then great.
你又给他们买了一条非常有趣或独特的，那也不错。
But it is good to take the time to get somebody something they really like or they would really
但花时间给别人买他们真正喜欢、真正会用或
use or enjoy.
享受的东西是好的。
Exactly.
没错。
So what kind of gifts do you plan to give this holiday season?
那么这个假期你打算送什么礼物呢？
Do you celebrate Christmas?
你庆祝圣诞节吗？
Let us know on our website EnglishPod.com.
在我们的网站EnglishPod.com上告诉我们吧。
Right.
对。
We'll see you guys there.
我们到时候见。
And until next time.
下次再见。
Bye.
拜拜。
Cheers
干杯